and I'm chatting with Jim Bradley about his recollections of working at Texas A&M.
Okay, that click is still going.
I think I did not get the date on here, January the 26th.
Jim, give us your full name and describe briefly
give us a brief biographical summary of your life before you came to A&M as an employee.
No, let's get on up to when you're employed.
Okay, I'm James R. Bradley.
I took full employment with the Texas Engineering Experiment Station in November 1951.
I was born February 13th, 1923, in Alveston, Texas.
And started at Texas Indian University in September 1940.
Where'd you grow up and go to high school?
I grew up in the little town of Alta Loma, Texas.
It's in Alveston County.
It was right in the depth of the Depression when we moved to Alta Loma in 1929.
He had bought a little house, five extra land, and when the depression hit, he moved from Galveston to Alta Loma, Texas, a town of about 200 population.
And I started school in Alta Loma in 1929.
And they lived in Alta Loma right until the time that I enrolled in Texas Indian University in 1940.
Thank you.
When my dad moved to Alta Loma, he had been a craftsman, he'd been a carpenter, and then a contractor, and of course he lost all that during the Depression.
And when he moved to Alta Loma, he started a dairy, and he kept that dairy until 1944, when the war was at its height, and it was impossible for him to get any help.
He sold out, retired.
I went into the service.
You want me to go into that?
I was in the Corps of Cadets at A&M University and had a contract.
And I was in the class in 1942.
It started going year-round.
We got three full semesters.
In March of 1940, in March,
of 1943, we were called into the service and taken and put over to San Antonio.
And we was actually given private pay and uniforms until May of 1943.
Let's see, it's 1943.
We still lack one semester from graduating, because we've only got the seven semesters here.
So they took us out, I like 12 hours from graduating, and they split us all up.
Our classes split up, some went into artillery, some went into various branches of the service.
I went into the tank destroyer.
They asked for a group of A&M students, along with other military teaching students who wanted to volunteer.
I volunteered for it.
And then about in 1st of July, after we stayed at Fort Sam about six weeks, 1st of July they sent a group of us that were going to Texas Toronto School to Fort Benning Yard to go to what they call a pre-OCS class.
And we stayed there until we got our order to go to Fort Hood, which is in the late summer of 1940.
And there was about seven or eight of us Aggies in that OCS class.
And after we got the OCS, we got car commissions as second lieutenant, which was about in October of 1943.
Tank destroyer battalion was a new component of military.
And we then went into training units.
You want me to keep going on that?
Mm-hm.
Okay.
We got trained, went on into training units, and I was assigned to a tank destroyer battalion as a platoon leader, a reconnaissance platoon, and stayed in that
unit until about 243.
Stayed in that unit for about five or six months.
Then I was called up to be an instructor in the tank of drawers, OCS, a machine gun, 30 caliber machine gun instructor, which I stayed in that position until
I was sent overseas about the first week in January of 1944 as a replacement officer and this was getting toward the closing of the war.
France.
And it was in the winter, cold winter.
And occasionally, if they needed replacements, I was assigned to a tank of strong battalion.
In France, I'm trying to think of the town.
See, that's what I'm going to do for.
No worries.
And then I would, my unit that I was attached to, the platoon leader is the place that I texted.
I had been hurt during the war.
So I took over a platoon, it was a seasoned platoon.
They had been in combat for approximately a year and a half.
My first taste of combat was in Stuttgart, Germany.
It was an objective that was assigned to us as a tanker to support the infantry that was ahead of us, which we did.
We went from Stuttgart then
The rest of my time was going from Stuttgart to the various towns and cities until we got to Munich, Germany.
And my protagonist, our protagonist, was the first protagonist that I know of to be assigned to the concentration camp Dalkau.
And we got there about, we got into Munich about
11, 30, and 12 o'clock at night with our tank destroyers.
And of course, as you realize, we had the whole supportive infantry that was ahead of us.
And we was assigned a duty to, my platoon was assigned a duty to take over one portion of the Dalcon that was facing one of the streets.
It was there that we could see the people being loaded into boxcars.
Some of them were certainly alive, both of them did.
And they kept my battalion stayed there in the platoon.
My battalion stayed there for about 36 hours.
And then we were relieved and sent down to concentration camp Hallow.
which was about... How do you spell that one?
A-L-L-A-C-H. We got there, and that was a typhus fever camp.
So as we approached Alok, the people had to divide in two sections, limited one section, limited the other.
And they were all very, very hungry.
It was all coming up to the high fence and they come up to the fence.
And we were ordered not to supply them food in the tank destroyers.
We always used to carry a lot of food, sea rations and various Army rations.
And we were cautioned not to give these people a prison concentration hell off in India.
any food because it would be more harmful to them and it would be good because their system was used to.
But anyway, we were relieved.
We stayed there just about two or three nights.
And, of course, the medics come in right after we did.
The medics took over everything as far as the prisoners, and all we did was put up a guard around the camp to keep anyone from there.
As far as you could tell, these people in the concentration camps, were they all Jewish or what?
No, there was a lot of Polish people in there.
There may have been a lot of Jews in there too.
We didn't go, that was a very low priority of who they were, they were human beings.
Yeah, yeah.
And I'll tell you the truth, I can't, the only reason I said Polish is because several of them was carrying signs and I assumed that was their name, the Polish names.
But we only stayed there about two or three nights and then they sent us down to Rosenheim, Germany.
And that's when our battalion, see in the tank destroyers, a platoon of tank destroyers was assigned to a battalion of infantry.
So we all got the entire 692nd tank destroyer battalion which I was assigned to.
We all come into Rosenheim and met for the first time as a battalion in several months.
And we stayed in Rosenheim about
a week.
And each platoon was signed to town.
I was signed to town with Solheben, Germany, S-O-L-H-E-B-E-N, I think is the way it's spelled, Solheben, Germany.
And I stayed there for about, oh, maybe, around July the 15th.
I stayed there probably three or four weeks.
And then they sent my platoon down to Kosin, Austria, that's K-O-S-S-E-I-N, Kosin, Austria, in occupation.
And we stayed there until we got our orders to come back to the States.
And we left out of Kosin, Austria.
And it had just boxcars.
And we loaded up 30 and 40 to the boxcar.
And come all the way from Coast and Austria to Paris, France.
We was in Camp Lucky Strike, which is a camp right out of Paris.
And we got there, and we were, at that time, we reprocessed and processed again to check to see if we were physically in good shape and so forth.
And we stayed in Camp Lucky Strike probably 10 to 14 days somewhere.
And we were put then on a liberty ship.
And we were about, well, it was in the English Channel.
We'd been out at sea maybe a couple of days or been on a liberty ship for two or four days.
And we were halted.
The first bomb is dropped in Japan, the first atomic bomb is dropped.
And we didn't know that, but we stopped and later found out that's the reason they delayed our ship.
We stayed out the channel, right outside the channel, for about four or five days, I guess.
And they brought us on into Camp Costanage in Boston.
And we got to Camp Costanage, Miles Standage.
Then we were all taken out to go home.
I got a 45-day leave after we were processed to take a physical leave.
So you'd been gone how many?
Two years?
No, no, no, no, no.
This is only...
This is fall of 45.
Yeah, well, I went... You went overseas in 44, didn't you?
That's right, into 44.
So I'd only been overseas about seven or eight months.
As you look back on that experience in Europe,
What did those months, what effect did those months have on your view of people and of life?
Well, I had several experiences that have been a major change in my life.
I had a platoon and all young boys, all young men, and I was very young.
I was only in 1945, I was only 22, 45.
I guess the major change we were in, as I say, I was in the tank control.
It was a small organization.
We had a medium-sized tank.
We could carry our own food.
We could carry, you know, we had clothes that we carried on the tanks.
We had to, if it was cold, the tanks were always warm for the motor running, so we had that.
But we had, the thing when you went into occupation,
after the war was easily over.
We were just in the Bavarian Alps, close to Austria, in the Bavarian Alps.
And Sol Huben, Germany, joined in the Bavarian Alps.
So there still was a lot of essence troopers coming down out of the Alps.
And we had, when they signed us a town, when I say they, my platoon was signed a town of Sol Huben.
That means we had to cut off all influences into the town.
We couldn't let anybody in, couldn't let anybody out.
And everybody had to have a ration, a food ration card.
So my job, myself and my sergeant, was issuing ration cards.
So we lived in the program master's house, which is the mayor's house.
And we got them all out of there.
All the people that remember got them.
And then we turned that into our headquarters.
And we only had a very short period of time to get them registered with their cards so they could get food, enough food coming in and out.
And when we posted our card, I had a young man who was
just like any normal young man.
There was no difference in him than all the rest of them that had come up with him.
When we posted that guard, for some reason, he got hysterical.
It was just an entrance to the gate there.
And so the sergeant who was posting the guard come back up the top and brought me back down there.
In the meantime, he left him with another guard.
And the young man was
And I guess that had one of the greatest fingerprints on him.
Because he didn't, he had never shown any signs of anything up to this time.
And we got him back, got him back, got him calmed down, and of course we shipped him to the back line so he could get medical help.
I never did hear whatever happened to him after that.
But to see somebody that would just crack up after the war was over, standing out
He walked Gardner Street to keep people coming in to crack up.
I guess he reached, that was a culmination of a lot of things.
That always has had a tremendous impression because I always feel good this way.
Haskell, if that could happen to him for what he had been through, that could happen to any one of us right today with some of the conditions we're living in.
He could call it getting cracked.
And there were several others, but that one always stood out on me.
I can still see the young man right in that business.
Alright, so you came home on leave and you're discharged when?
I come home, I got home in, oh, I guess it was October because they kept us at Fort Sam Houston checking us all out.
It was around October 1st when I got home.
After I got my 45-day leave, see that put me up to November, I would sign to Camp Swift in Bastrop because that's where all of our equipment was coming into.
All of our tanks and everything was coming into Swift.
So we had to report there and then we had to get these tanks off our inventory and things up to all of them.
And then I went on annual leave
I went on, they put me on annual leave till my retirement savings, so I didn't have to come back.
I could be going to Fortwood, but I could get out.
So I took my annual leave, and of course I was engaged to be married, too.
And I got out of the Army, and my end of the tour of Mama B was April 8th.
I got married April 2nd.
Five, six days before.
Now this young lady had waited for you
No.
Well, we knew each other.
Oh, okay.
But actually, we didn't start coming reasonably close until I got back in a little seat.
So you got serious then.
Pretty serious.
Then you come to A&M.
Then I come back to A&M in June of 46.
Year after?
45.
Okay, 46.
War's over.
My wife and I come back to school here, and that's when we got the apartment in Hart Hall.
You know, they were signed out by the number of artists you liked from graduating.
I liked 12 artists from graduating.
So we got an apartment in Hart Hall, which was a mansion compared to what they were living in, because it was all the married veterans and all of them had come up and hit in 46.
And so I stayed in Hart Hall.
until I got my bachelor's degree, and then I stayed on one semester in graduate school.
And I would stay longer, except Dr. Roy Smith, who was our doctor, told us in November that my wife was pregnant.
So you had to get to work.
So we cut, I cut our graduate school short in January, and in January, when I got my degree, we moved to Dallas.
I had a job with Ogall Cup.
The mobile oil company had a training program.
It was the first one they ever had the year I got on.
It was the first one they'd ever had.
And as you recall, the petroleum industry employees was all, they got deferred.
And when I went to work on a road gun, I was on this training program with two other young men.
One was a graduate of the University of Oklahoma and the other was a graduate of Rice.
And that was a shock to my system because when we
went to report to work for the Mobile Oil Company, and the three of us had all been military people.
Actually, we got a feeling, or maybe I could.
Now, I know the three of us all got the same feeling, that we were the lucky ones to get to go to war.
They were the unlucky ones that had to stay there.
I even had them tell me, well, you had steak in Normandy.
We didn't have steak.
We couldn't get gasoline.
You had all the gasoline you wanted.
And it took me a little doing
What was your pay on that first job?
$235 a month.
That was another thing.
The people that was up there that had worked 20, 25 years, their salary was $200 a month.
And so the word got out that we were getting this $235 a month, and that didn't go too well.
And you stayed with Mobile?
Five years.
And came to A&M?
In 1951.
What was your title?
And your assignment when you came?
Well, I left Mogul.
I left a good future at Mogul, and I knew that.
I come here to get my graduate, finish up on a master's degree.
And I come on as a research assistant in the Texas Engineering Experimentation in what they call the Industrial Development Department at that time.
And I went on and got my master's degree.
In what?
In agriculture economics.
or liberal arts schools.
You know, there was no colleges back then.
All your business coaches were taught in NAGECO.
And that's when I got my bachelor's degree in marketing finance in NAGECO.
But anyway, when we started back in 51, and I got that degree in 54, I don't know.
Pretty short.
Take it too long.
But...
That was a time when they decided they were going to put a lot of these organizations on self-support, generate your own income.
I don't remember whether it was 54, I think it was 54, 55, that the engineering department station was told, you know, that you guys would be self-supporting.
And Calhoun could take the office to do that exercise.
But anyway, we had, it was only about seven or eight in the industrial development department.
I guess out of that 7-8, there was probably only about two that had any interest in becoming self-supported.
So after, in 57, that was about two years later, none of the budgets weren't being made.
And so they had to make a reduction in staff.
So at that time, and Calhoun goes on, this exercise really well, they had brought on a PhD by the name of Dr. Aaron Rose.
Aaron Rose.
A-A-R-O-N Rose, R-O-S-E. And Aaron had come from ministry, and so this didn't scare him at all about becoming self-supporting.
Fred Benson was dean.
But Aaron Rose was made vice director.
They didn't make him director.
They let Fred Benson keep the title of director.
Aaron Rose would become director.
And so when he come in, I'm sure he must have been told, you know, you've got to make your way.
Well, first thing he did was call all of us in and ask us how we felt about that.
I mean, individually.
I didn't see anything wrong with it.
I told him that.
I said, you know, I can't make your own way.
It must not be needed.
That was my philosophy.
It still is my philosophy.
But, so anyway, in 1958, he called me up one day and said, I'm going to make you head of industrial economics.
And he said, here's your budget, here's how much you've got to make, here's what you've got to do.
So I went back, and I called each one of them in one at a time, told them exactly the same thing Aaron told me, that we had one year to get to this budget.
Do you want to participate?
I want to participate.
And by January,
That year, six of them volunteered and decided to leave.
And they left me and one of them was Bill Shelton.
Who?
Bill Shelton.
As you think about it now, what was the function of the Engineering Extension Service?
That's an experiment.
What was the function of it then?
Well, applied research.
We had the heat pump research lab.
We had architectural research.
We had cotton seed processing research.
What was the most highly visible?
The area that most people would...
The heat pump.
The heat pump?
Yes.
That's my opinion.
I don't know the details of all these elements.
About how many people worked for the experiment station then?
Very few.
Two dozen?
Okay.
Describe this man, Rose, his personality, where he came from, his style.
I can't tell you.
He comes from California, and we hired him, but I don't think he's in California.
And when he left, he went back.
By the way, he only lasted about two years, and he went back to California.
He was from business, and he and I hit it off real well.
He had a lot of energy.
He was a man of few words.
He never had any doubt about how he felt about the things.
To me, he was very easy to get along with.
Every month he had a lot of conflicts because he didn't stay very well.
But I never had that relationship with him.
Who succeeded him?
Well, then they went to the director.
Okay.
Of course, Benson was always, and from then on, Benson stayed director until Porter took it over the last year or two before he left.
And then they come in with associate directors.
And who was that after, or do you remember?
Well, who were the key associate directors?
Well, I can't tell you the dates on these.
Harry Whitmore became the associate director.
And then we had three or four kennels that come in as associate directors.
Describe Harry Whitmore's style.
Harry Whitmore was pretty much, his style was pretty much letting you do what you know you have to do.
Letting you alone, never bothering you.
I don't guess I ever had an adverse meeting with, well I never had an adverse meeting with any of them as far as necessary my whole life.
Harry never interfered with what you did.
Harry never did interfere with what I did.
I'm a great person on policies and procedures.
And I, at one time, when I left the Institute, they said, I could practically tell you every paragraph in that policy and procedure.
And as a result, I stayed within the policies and procedures.
I did not try to get to the left or to the right.
Now, sometimes I made a decision that may have stopped being that way, but that's not the way I interpreted the policies and procedures.
So, he never bothered me at all.
But that, Harry Stigman, associate director, he left shortly after Richardson came in.
About, can you give me some examples of Whitmore's important decisions, examples of his style?
Well, if you knew Fred Benson very well,
Fred made the decisions for him to make an experiment station, and rightfully so, because he was going to get the credit of the plane as being director.
Basically, Harry just kept the ship floating.
It didn't get wobbly or it didn't sink.
But as far as any major decisions, I'm just giving you my relationships with him.
There was never anything that I could see.
I felt very comfortable with me.
I could go and talk to him, just like I could talk to you.
There was never any ill feelings.
When we left, we always met at peace.
When the conversation ended, was his desire always clearly understood?
Did he communicate clearly?
This might sound rare to you, but I don't think we ever had a position, either one of us was never in a position where I felt that he was in the wrong or he felt that I was in the wrong.
We never, Harry and I never had, I don't guess I met with Harry.
How long was he there?
12, 15 years, 20 years?
I went to the Engineering Defense Service in 73.
So he had only been there about seven or eight years.
Alright, let's go back to this man, Fred Benson.
Was he here when you went to work?
Sure.
He was in the Civil Engineering Department.
In Civil Engineering.
Dr. Mello, at that time, Dr. Arthur Mello was Director of the Engineering Experimentation.
M-I-L-L?
M-E-L-L-O-H.
Very, very fine person.
And he left here and went to Dean of Engineering in Kansas somewhere.
Okay.
And so when did Fred Benson move up?
After Calhoun.
Right.
Oh, that's right.
Let's bring in Calhoun.
Okay.
Calhoun come in, my best of memories, Calhoun come in here about in 55.
Describe your impression.
See, Barlow was Dean before him.
Well, there was so much distance between me and him, I didn't get to really know Calhoun until about probably late 50s.
When did he come down?
55?
I didn't think so, in the mid-50s.
I didn't really have any dealings with Dr. Calhoun until about 1960, probably.
And I don't remember how our relationship started out, because Fred Benson was director of the International Transportation at that time.
But anyway, Dr. Calhoun and I met.
And then in its early 60s,